{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this letter, the writer claims that, “It is essential that public opinion should be enlightened” in a section on the education of the masses. The writer of this letter claims that the “alternate domination of one faction over another is itself a frightful despotism.” In this letter, the writer states that, “The shade of retirement is as necessary to me as it will be welcome.” Written and published in September, 1796, for ten points, name this final presidential statement written by the owner of Mount Vernon.",
      "answer": "George Washington’s Farewell Address A"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization lost nearly 10,000 men at an engagement at Raate Road where it was defeated by Hjalmar Siilasvuo. While head of this organization, Mikhail Frunze defeated Baron Wrangel during a civil war. Georgy Zhukov once commanded this organization whose flag shows an unfilled yellow star against the backdrop of its namesake color. For ten points, name this armed force that was created after the 1917 Russian Revolution and that opposed the White Army.",
      "answer": "Workers’ and Peasants’ Red Army"
    },
    {
      "question": "Keith Quincy controversially claimed that this ethnic group had an independent kingdom from 400R-900 AD. The Spirit Catches You and You Fall Down by Anne Fadiman tells of the struggles of an immigrant family from this ethnic group living in Merced, California, a community with some 5000 of these people. A subgroup of the Miao, the CIA recruited thousands of these people to fight in the Indochina Wars. For ten points, name this often persecuted ethnic minority from China and southeast Asia.",
      "answer": [
        "Hmong",
        "Hmoob"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was shot during a 1977 siege during which Hanafi Muslims took 149 hostages at the District DBuilding. This man served as the first chairman of SNCC [SNICK] and protested the 1972 blaxploitation film Super Fly by forming a group called BANG. This man succeeded Walter Washington in his most prominent position and won a fourth term in that mayoral role in spite of having been caught on videotape smoking crack in 1990. For ten points, name this longtime mayor of Washington, D.C.",
      "answer": "Marion Barry"
    },
    {
      "question": "British officers in India created a variant of this sport in the nineteenth century using books and bottle corks. Jaques [JAKES] of London popularized a common name for this sport whose notable players include Jan-Ove Waldner and Zhang Yining. The penhold grip is often used by players from East Asia who play this sport, considered an Olympic “racket” sport since its introduction in 1988 even though it is played with a paddle. For ten points, name this sport sometimes called “ping pong.”",
      "answer": [
        "Table tennis",
        "ping pong until mentioned T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man won the Battle of Zapote Bridge, but his brother was killed during the subsequent Battle of Perez Dasmarinas. This man was brought aboard the USS Vicksburg after being captured by the Macabebe Scouts of Frederick Funston in Palanan. This leader lost a 1935 presidential election to Manuel Quezon. For ten points, name this revolutionary leader who issued the Philippine Declaration of F Independence and was the first President of the Philippines.",
      "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state saw more than 200 battles in the American Revolutionary War, beginning with the first Battle of Ninety Six. The largest surrender of American soldiers in the Revolutionary War took place in this state after a defeat for Benjamin Lincoln, whereas another setback in this state featured Horatio Gates’s loss at Camden. The fortunes of the colonists in this state fared better near the Broad River. For A ten points, name this state where Daniel Morgan was victorious at Cowpens.",
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "While sailing for this group, Paul Beneke was put on trial for seizing a triptych from England. This group held drittel meetings in preparation for a central “meeting ride,” or Tagfahrt. This group was harassed by the Likedeelers after pushing the Victual Brothers out of Gotland. This group imposed a tax on Haakon VI and his father-in-law in the Treaty of Stralsund. Centered at Lubeck, for ten points, name this German confederation of merchant guilds. R",
      "answer": [
        "Hanseatic League",
        "Hansa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An economic advisor to this man named Fuad Shubaki alleged that this man allocated aid money for buying weaponry. The Madrid Conference of 1991 attempted to broker a peace between this man’s organization and a national government. A Mukataa in Ramallah served as the central compound of this leader after he signed a 1995 agreement with Yitzhak Rabin known as the Oslo Accord. For ten points, name this longtime chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization.",
      "answer": [
        "Yasser Arafat",
        "Abu Ammar D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man told a graduating class to “be ashamed to die until you have won some victory for humanity” while president of Antioch College. This man succeeded to John Quincy Adams’s House seat and criticized Daniel Webster for his support of the Compromise of 1850. After a trip to Prussia, this man founded The Common School Journal reflecting one of his main principles that the “public should no longer remain ignorant.” For ten points, name this Massachusetts education reformer.",
      "answer": "Horace Mann T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, three Black teenagers were killed by police officers in the Algiers Motel Incident. A mayor who resisted deploying the National Guard duFring this event stated, “Today we stand amidst the ashes of our hopes.” This event began when police arrested 82 people celebrating the return of Vietnam veterans at an illegal bar. Mayor Jerome Cavanagh failed to prevent this event, the bloodiest of the “long, hot summer.” For ten points, name this 1967 event in the largest city in Michigan.",
        "answer": [
          "1967 Detroit race riot",
          "12th Street Riot,",
          "Algiers Motel Incident before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the 12th Street Riot, this governor of Michigan called in the National Guard. This Mormon 1968 presidential caAndidate’s son was the Republican nominee for president in 2012.",
        "answer": "George Wilcken Romney"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This polarizing leader of the Social Democrats promoted women’s rights, helped save nuclear power in his nation, and notably called apartheid “a particularly gruesome system.” This man promoted the release of the documentary They Call Us Misfits that put a spotlight on “junkie” culture in Stockholm. This successor of Tage [TAG-eh] Erlander is officially thought to have been murdered by drug addict Christer Pettersson. For ten points, name this Swedish Prime Minister. R",
        "answer": "Olof Palme"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Olof Palme was particularly critical of this South African politician who became the last Prime Minister of South Africa after he abolished the position and became State President in 1984.",
        "answer": "Pieter Willem Botha"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s father commanded US forces during the Gulf of Tonkin Incident. In the summer of 1965, this man’s poetry impressed fellow UCLA cinematography student, Ray Manzarek, and they formed a D band with a name inspired by Aldous Huxley’s 1954 work about his psychedelic experiences. This man became one of the most influential singers and songwriters in history with number one hits such as “Hello, I Love You” and “Light My Fire.” For ten points, name this man, known as the “Lizard King,” who fronted The Doors.",
        "answer": "Jim Morrison"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jim Morrison was laid to rest in Pere Lachaise Cemetery in Paris, the site of many famous burials, but this composer of William Tell and The Barber of Seville was moved from there to his home city of Florence twenty years after his death.",
        "answer": "Gioachino Rossini T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle has been called “the day of the dead moon” due to a solar eclipse during the retreat of Anthony Durnford’s men in the face of an assault by Ntshingwayo Khoza. One side’s Martini-Henry guns in this battle could not break a determined impi charge, leading to the recall of Lord Chelmsford as commander. Fought on the same day as the nearby Rorke’s Drift, for ten points, name this disaster for F the United Kingdom, the first major battle of the Anglo-Zulu War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Isandlwana"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The British troops of the 24th of Foot gave the hill of Isandlwana this nickname, because it reminded them of a 4500 year old limestone monument they had seen while fighting Napoleon in Giza.",
        "answer": "The Sphinx A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s explorations of Alaska were chronicled in his book The Cruise of the Corwin. This man described the Calypso Borealis flower in one of his many correspondences with Jeanne Carr. With William Colby, this man led a campaign against a dam proposed by James D. Phelan. This man is best known for founding an organization in 1892 which advocated for federal acquisition of Yosemite. For ten points, name this environmental activist who founded the Sierra Club.",
        "answer": "John Muir"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among those who urged the preservation of the Yosemite Valley was this noted landscape arcRhitect who worked with Calvert Vaux on the design of New York City’s Central Park.",
        "answer": "Frederick Law Olmsted"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThisstatewasthesiteofthefirstsuccessfulrecallofagovernorinUShistory,targetedatLynnFrazier in 1921. Another governor of this state, William “Wild Bill” Langer, barricaded himself in the governor’s mansion and declared this state independent after he was removed from office. In 1873, the North Pacific Railway changed this state’s capital from Edwinton in a move to attract German immigrants. For ten points, name this state that may or may not have entered the Union before its neighbor in 1889. D",
        "answer": "North Dakota BONUS:WhenthispresidentsignedthestatehoodpapersforNorthandSouthDakota,hewasdeliberately unaware of which was signed first. Name this president, the only man to both succeed and precede the same person as president. ANSWER: Benjamin Harrison T 7 This author profiled a member of the Communist Party in the 1967 essay “Comrade Laski, C.P.U.S.A. M.L..” This author won a 2005 Pulitzer for a book describing life after the death of her husband, John Gregory Dunne. An essay by this author is titled after a quote from Yeats’s “Second Coming” and describes the Summer of Love in Haight-Ashbury. For ten points, name this author of The Year of Magical F Thinking and Slouching Toward Bethlehem. ANSWER: Joan Didion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Joan Didion suffered from this disease of the nervous system, named for the scars it leaves on the brain, from which Saint Lidwina, Congresswoman Barbara Jordan, and comedian Richard Pryor also suffered.",
        "answer": [
          "Multiple Sclerosis",
          "Encephalomyelitis disseminata A"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Battle of Antietam",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Document issued as a result of the battle declaring slaves in seceding states to be free F",
          "answer": [
            "Emancipation Proclamation",
            "Proclamation 95"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Union army commander who later ran for President in 1864",
          "answer": "George McClellan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Maryland town near which it was fought that became the Confederate name for the battle",
          "answer": "Sharpsburg A"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who took command of the First Corps and later defeated Lee at Gettysburg",
          "answer": "George Meade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of a namesake detective agency who provided misleading information to the Union commander",
          "answer": "Allan Pinkerton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of the Confederate order discovered by Union troops wrapped around three cigars",
          "answer": "Special Order 191 R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Location where Union troops pierced the Confederate center, a site of heavy casualties",
          "answer": "Sunken Road"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate commander whose reinforcements came up from Harpers Ferry and repulsed the final Union attack",
          "answer": "Ambrose Perry Hill D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Punic Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Carthaginian military leader who campaigned in Italy during the Second Punic War F",
          "answer": "Hannibal Barca"
        },
        {
          "question": "North African Proboscideans used by Carthagianians during the crossing of the Alps",
          "answer": "War Elephant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman victory that ended the Second Punic War won by Scipio Africanus",
          "answer": "Batte of Zama A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman tactic of avoiding combat used in Italy during the Second Punic War",
          "answer": "Fabian strategy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman orator whose speeches ended with a call for the destruction of Carthage",
          "answer": [
            "Marcus Porcius Cato the Elder",
            "Cato the Censor,",
            "Cato the Wise"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Boarding device used by Roman naval forces, from the Latin for “crow”",
          "answer": "Corvus R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Carthaginian commander whose severed head was thrown into his brother’s camp after losing the Battle of the Metaurus",
          "answer": "Hasdrubal Barca"
        },
        {
          "question": "North African kingdom and Roman ally whose border raids partly precipitated the Third Punic War",
          "answer": "Numidia D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Great Jin Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country over which the Great Jin ruled in the 12th century F",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Border fortification that they extended to protect themselves from northern invaders",
          "answer": [
            "Great Wall",
            "Wanli Changcheng"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese dynasty whose northern portion they conquered, capturing its emperor at Kaifeng",
          "answer": "Song dynasty A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Substance used in fire lances against them at the Siege of De’an that they later copied",
          "answer": "Gunpowder"
        },
        {
          "question": "Manchurian people from whom their founder came",
          "answer": "Wanyan Jurchen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of Genghis Khan who completed their conquest by taking Kaifeng",
          "answer": "Ogedei Khan R"
        },
        {
          "question": "State that they conquered, expelling Yelu Deshi westward to found Kara Khitai",
          "answer": "Liao dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the dynasty, a chief of the Wanyan who united his people",
          "answer": [
            "Aguda",
            "Taizu of Jin D T"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Stephen Girard stayed to help victims of this event after Bush Hill and other medical facilities were found to have unqualified staffF. Matthew Clarkson was mayor during this event, during which the Free African Society volunteered to help victims. The (20 pts)",
        "unsanitary conditions of the central city were theorized by Benjamin Rush to have caused this event, which historians now think was initiated by Caribbean refugees. This event caused George Washington’s (10 pts)",
        "cabinet to reassemble in the nearby city of Germantown. For ten points, name this 1793 epidemic that affected the “City of Brotherly Love.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "1793 yellow fever epidemic in Philadelphia",
        "equivalents to “epidemic”, do not",
        "“pandemic” A"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s lawyer attempted to have him acquitted by saying he was a Prussian, to which this man exclaimed “I am French and will remain French!” During the French (20 pts)",
        "retreat from Russia, this man led the rearguard and was thus called “the last Frenchman in Russia.” Wellington’s forces at Quatre Bras were attacked by this man who joined up with his former commander after promising to bring him to Paris (10 pts)",
        "in an iron cage. This man led an unsupported cavalry charge and failed to spike British cannons at Waterloo, sealing his fate. For ten points, name this marshal of France under Napoleon. ANRSWER: Michel Ney (3) Carvings from this civilization include depictions of a shaman raising the World Tree such as in the San Martin Pajapan Monument. A common motif in this civilization was a half-man, half- (+) jaguar spirit known as the were [WAIR]-jaguar, frequently depicted on Kunz axes. One mark of rank in this civilization was the possession of jade masks. San Lorenzo and La Venta were artistic centers of this civilization whose most significant (*) sculptural achievements were typically formed from basalt. For ten points, name this Mesoamerican civilization that flourished from 1500 to 400 BC, best known for their giant stone heads. D"
      ],
      "answer": "Olmecs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The aggressor in this battle hoped to capitalize on the fact that its opponent’s armies were occupied besieging Hasedo. In this battle, Otani Yoshitsugu’s line broke after the previously neutral (20 pts)",
        "Kobayakawa Hideaki charged. One side was forced to retreat before this battle as Gifu Castle had already fallen. More than 160 thousand samurai gathered for this battle in 1600 with more than 30 thousand losing their lives. This battle was fought between (10 pts)",
        "Toyotomi loyalists like Ishida Mitsunari and a certain future shogun. For ten points, name this battle in which Tokugawa Ieyasu finalized his hold over Japan."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Sekigahara T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This holiday features the performance of passion plays called tazieh. In Lebanon, this holiday’s practice of tatbir has been partially replaced with a blood drive. This holiday commemorates a man who abandoned his (20 pts)",
        "Hajj when he learned that Yazid had sent assassins to kill him, leading to his death at Kufu instead. This holiday marks the peak of F the (10 pts)",
        "Remembrance of Muharram. For ten points, name this holiday on which the Shia commemorate the martyrdom of Husayn at the Battle of Karbala while the Sunni mark the day that God led the Israelites across the Red Sea."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yawm Ashura",
        "Muharram Remembrances",
        "Mourning of Muharram before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man avoided combat at Campbell’s Station but was finally caught at Knoxville. This A man successfully defended Fort Sanders from James Longstreet as head of the Department of the (20 pts)",
        "Ohio, a post he held when he ordered the arrest of Clement Vallandigham. One of this man’s offensives was thwarted by torrential rain leading to his replacement by (10 pts)",
        "Joseph Hooker. This man failed to seize Marye’s Heights from Robert E. Lee at Fredericksburg. For ten points, name this Union general whose military career ended after a disastrous loss at The Crater."
      ],
      "answer": "Ambrose Burnside"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Features along this construct included iron-cast bell-shaped “cloches” along with larger “ouRvrages.” This construct was panned in favor of mobility in the tract “Army of the Future” but was completed during the tenure of Chief of the Army Staff (20 pts)",
        "Maurice Gamelin. A lack of action near this structure led to the so-called Phony War, though this structure later proved to be (10 pts)",
        "ineffectual as the Wehrmacht slipped through the Ardennes Forest. For ten points, name this ineffectual French defensive line in World War Two, named for the French Minister of War."
      ],
      "answer": "Maginot Line D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to Appian, Hannibal once claimed that this man was the second greatest general of all time as “he was the first to teach the art of laying out a camp.” This man defeated Antigonus Gonatas at the Battle of the (20 pts)",
        "Aous but lost his firstborn son Ptolemy in a failed siege of Sparta. During street fighting in Argos, this man was killed after he was knocked unconscious by a (10 pts)",
        "tile thrown by an old woman. For ten points, name this Molossian king who defeated Rome at the Battles of Heraclea and Asculum after which he stated, “If we are victorious in one more battle with the Romans, we shall be utterly ruined.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Pyrrhus of Epirus T"
    }
  ]
}